Guide to the Lucy Randolph Mason Papers, 1910-1959 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lucy Randolph Mason papers 1910-1959 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mason, Lucy Randoph, 1882-1959.
12.0 linear feet Extent: Approximately 6500 items
Labor activist, public relations representative in the South for the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), and resident of Richmond, Virginia, and Atlanta, Georgia. The papers of Lucy Randolph Mason span the years 1910-1959, with the bulk of the papers dating between 1940-1954. The collection consists of correspondence, drafts of writings, memoranda, speeches, printed material, clippings, and miscellany. The most extensive correspondence begins in 1937 and relates to the development of labor unions in the South, attitudes of churches toward labor, conditions in textile mills, and blacks in the labor movement. There is also material on Georgia politics and government, especially the gubernatorial campaign of 1946, and the Roosevelt administration. Organizations mentioned frequently are the American Federation of Labor, the Southern Regional Council, the Highlander School in Monteagle, Tennessee, the Southern School for Workers in Richmond, the Southern Conference for Human Welfare, and the Southern Conference Education Fund. Correspondents include Jonathan Daniels, Allan S. Haywood of the CIO, Sidney Hillman, John L. Lewis, George Sinclair Mitchell, and Eleanor Roosevelt.
RL.00854
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lucy Randolph Mason papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1948 and 1954.
Biographical Note
Born in Virginia on July 26, 1882, Lucy Randolph Mason was the daughter of Rev. Landon Randolph and Lucy (Ambler) Mason. Among her ancestors were some of the most prominent names in Virginia at the time. Her parents instilled in her an active interest in social problems, and she devoted her long life to improving conditions for women, factory workers, and African Americans. Never attending college, Mason taught herself stenography and typing, went to work in a Richmond law office, and became active in the Richmond Equal Suffrage League and the League of Women Voters. She served as industrial, then general secretary of the Richmond Young Women's Christian Association from 1914-1932. In 1931 she was employed for two months by the National Consumers' Laue to work with the Southern Council on Women and Children in Industry in an attempt to create more favorable public attitudes toward child labor legislation and restrictions on working hours for women and children in factories.
In 1937 Mason moved to Atlanta to assume a post as Congress of Industrial Organizations' (CIO) relations representative for the Southeast U.S. Until her retirement 17 years later she was the CIO spokesperson in the South. During her time with the CIO, Mason represented labor interests during strikes, visited communities where the CIO was attempting to organize workers, attended many college conferences, made speeches, wrote articles, and carried on an extensive correspondence with labor leaders, politicians, journalists, manufacturers, and church representatives. Shortly before retiring in 1952, Mason published her memoirs, entitled To Win These Rights. Lucy Mason died in 1959 at the age of 77.
Collection Overview
The papers of Lucy Randolph Mason span the years 1910-1959, with the bulk of the papers dating between 1940-1954. The collection consists of correspondence, drafts of writings, memoranda, speeches, printed material, clippings, and miscellany. The correspondence prior to 1937 largely concerns Mason's work with the Richmond League of Women Voters. There is much material relating to her southern tour in 1931 but very little on the YWCA and none on the National Consumer's League. The most extensive correspondence begins in 1937 and relates to the development of labor unions in the South, attitudes of churches toward labor, conditions in textile mills, antiwar sentiments, blacks in the labor movement, and race relations in general. There is also material on Georgia politics and government, especially the gubernatorial campaign of 1946, and the Roosevelt administration.
Organizations mentioned frequently are the American Federation of Labor and its competition with the CIO, the Southern Regional Council, the Highlander School in Monteagle, Tenn., the Southern School for Workers in Richmond, the Southern Conference for Human Welfare, and the Southern Conference Education Fund. Correspondents include Jonathan Daniels, Allan S. Haywood of the CIO, Sidney Hillman, John L. Lewis, George Sinclair Mitchell, and Eleanor Roosevelt.
There are two boxes of speeches written by Mason, and there are several speeches also by Henry A. Wallace. The collection also includes notes and the typescript for her book, To Win These Rights. Minutes, memoranda, and other materials are filed together and are concerned largely with Mason's union work and philanthropic interests. Print materials include publications from a variety of labor and social welfare organizations, in the form of leaflets, pamphlets, and broadsides. There are also many folders of clippings, arranged by decades, dealing with labor unions, Georgia politics, and the administrations of Roosevelt and Truman.
Subject Headings
Daniels, Jonathan, 1902-1981; Haywood, Allan S.; Hillman, Sidney; Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969; Mason, Lucy Randoph, 1882-1959; Mitchell, George Sinclair, 1902-1962; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Highlander Folk School (Monteagle, Tenn.); Southern School for Workers (Richmond, Va.); Labor -- Religious aspects -- Christianity -- Southern States; Textile workers -- Southern States; African American labor union members; Labor unions -- Southern States; Women labor union members -- Southern States; Women radicals -- Southern States -- Correspondence; Working class -- Southern States
Related Material
Published biography by John Salmond, Miss Lucy of the CIO: the Life and Times of Lucy Randolph Mason, 1882-1959. Also appears to be title of unpublished MA thesis by Margaret Lee Neustadt, UNC Chapel Hill, 1970.
Duke Libraries and UNC Chapel Hill
Description of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1918-1954 and undated, (8 boxes)
  - 1918-1940 Apr. (Box 1)
  - 1940 May-1942 May (Box 2)
  - 1942 June-1944 Sept. (Box 3)
  - 1944 Oct.-1947 Feb. (Box 4)
  - 1947 Mar.-1948 July (Box 5)
  - 1948 Aug.-1949 (Box 6)
  - 1950-1951 Apr. (Box 7)
  - 1951 May-1954 and undated (Box 8)
- Papers Series, 1931-1953 and undated, (7 boxes) (Box 8)
  - Addresses, 1931-1949 (Box 9)
  - Drafts and typescript of To Win These Rights (Box 10)
  - Addresses, 1950-1953 and undated (Box 11)
  - Minutes, 1946-1952 (Box 11)
  - Memoranda, 1938-1953 and undated (Box 11)
  - Miscellany, 1920-1940 (Box 11)
  - Miscellany, 1941-1946 (Box 12)
  - Miscellany, 1947-1949 (Box 13)
  - Miscellany, 1950-1953 (Box 14)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box 15)
- Clippings Series, 1910-1959 and undated, (6 boxes) (Box 15)
  - 1910-1939 (Box 16)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 17)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 18)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 19)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 20)
  - Undated (Box 21)
  - Volumes (Box 21)
- Printed Material Series, 1912-1954, (4 boxes) (Box 21)
  - 1912-1945 (Box 22)
  - 1946-1948 (Box 23)
  - 1949-1951 (Box 24)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 25)
- Oversized Materials, (1 box) (Box 25)
  - Printed material, National Union Farmer, 1945 Feb. (Box OV 21)